On the path to spatial intelligence, generating pixels that are truly spatially contextualized and grounded, that is the very hard step that Atlas has taken. We know LLMs are built on next token prediction. We've seen video models as being built on next frame prediction. Atlas is really new view prediction. This is the real place where AI can actually unlock a ton of...
value for people in their process. We're saying like 50, 100x reduction. There was a famous shot in the first Matrix movie where Neo is falling down. Exactly, they had hundreds of cameras viewing that angle on a green screen. On Atlas, we can do this with just three cameras. No studio capture, no green screen, no expensive calibration. No one has ever seen this result. When you set out to do this, did you know it was gonna work? I was pretty sure. Each time we made the model bigger, and each time we trained it for longer, it got significantly better. Does that mean we're gonna get 40 video? Like go walk around.
Language models are built around predicting the next token. What happens when a model instead learns to predict the next view of the world? In this episode, our team, Casado, sits down with World Lab's co-founders, Fei-Fei Li, Justin Johnson, and Ben Mildenhall to discuss ATLAS and the broader challenge of building AI that can reason about physical space. They explain how ATLAS combines generation and 3D reconstruction, why the team chose new view prediction as its underlying primitive.
and what they learned trying to scale an approach that hadn't been tested before. They also get into what's still missing, including richer dynamics and interaction, and how world models could eventually connect simulation with robotics and planning. Underlying it all is a bigger hypothesis. Could new view prediction play a similar role for spatial intelligence that next token prediction has played for language?
So big day yesterday you launched a new frontier model. She's got an amazing reception which is still coming in. I think maybe a good way to structure this conversation Let's just talk about exactly what that was and then we'll go back to history and work our way back up So maybe Justin you want to talk about what was launched yesterday why it's significant? Yeah, so Atlas is our new next-generation world model It has three basic things that can generate reconstruct and simulate the world So within that there's a couple different major capabilities. It has really good camera conditioned generation
So you can input an image together with a camera trajectory and steer the model and have it generate video frames, any perspective you want. It's really good at sparse 3D reconstruction. You can input one or multiple up to 100 frames that are views of the real world and use those to reconstruct the real world. And that reconstruction can take the case either of novel a video flying through the space or an explicit 3D reconstruction of the space. Then finally it can be used for simulation. And for this we show off these awesome bullet time videos which got a lot of attention online.
And then also robotic simulation. What's a bullet time video? A bullet time video. This comes from the Matrix. There was a famous shot in the first Matrix movie where Neo was like falling down. Oh, yeah. Exactly. So, and then remember in that famous shot, he's falling down, it's in slow motion and the camera flies all the way around. The way that they did that shot is they had a ring of hundreds of cameras. So then he fell over in the studio, they had hundreds of cameras viewing that angle on a green screen. And then they used those hundreds and hundreds of cameras to make that famous shot in Matrix. But now with Atlas, we can do this with as few as three cameras.
So no studio capture, no green screen, no expensive calibration. We can literally stick three iPhones onto iPods, use these to take sort of a video of something happening, like someone shooting a basket, someone dropping a strawberry into a bowl of milk. And then from those three iPhone videos, we can then reframe the shot and imagine like freeze time, have the camera fly in as the milk is splashing up and get these amazing frozen time views. And we can do this with just a couple of cameras. What is the simplest description of what Atlas does? What goes in and what comes out?
Yeah, so one of the really core principles of Atlas, the most fundamental thing is it does new view prediction. And this is a really fundamental primitive that we think is super exciting, a super new primitive for base models that no one's ever done before. Right, so we know LLMs are built on next token prediction. We've seen video models as being built on next frame prediction. Atlas is really new view prediction, right? That given some number of views of a scene or a description of a scene, those go into what we call a spatial context that describes implicitly what is the world that we want to talk about.
Then you can point a virtual camera at an arbitrary point in space and time, and Atlas will understand what that world is supposed to look like from that position in space and time. Ben, the video models out there all claiming to be world models and all claiming to have novel views. Can you maybe tease apart more concretely how this is different from the myriad models that have come before? Yeah, I think what Justin was saying about the spatial context aspect is super important here.
Many video models, a lot of video models actually got their claim to fame from their single image input or their start to last frame interpolation. Now we're starting to see models that can do this kind of omni-referencing with 20, 30, 50 images. But what's key with Atlas is that it actually has a kind of like spatially grounded meaning to every frame you put into it. So it's not just an image that the model is going to interpret whatever way it wants, or you can kind of try to argue with it and the text prompting and get it to do something specific with Atlas.
Every image actually has an associated three-dimensional camera pose and that means that you can perform this task of reconstruction with an extremely high degree of precision, right? So if we had four views of this room, one at each corner, you can put those into the model and then get an exact replication of everything you see in this room. And it's not going to guess what's in the other corner, like the relationship between things. It's just going to reproduce exactly what you give it. And you can also do that in a kind of creative or imaginative sense too. If you take two photos from
Different AI generations or real-world locations you can actually position and stage those to build these kind of intentionally directed fly-throughs that are really governed by exactly the precise place that you put the content you want and where the camera is going to look and travel. Which is very different I think than the kind of like more slot machine effect you get of having to retry generations over and over with just that kind of higher level of text control you get with video models. Is this just kind of an obvious
Scaled-up version of a traditional video model or is it a new architecture? I think it's a pretty new thing for a couple different reasons. One, but we talk about is it does both generation and reconstruction jointly in the same model. Like Ben was saying, this thing can take a couple views of this room and then reconstruct everything in this room exactly as you see it. And historically, reconstruction has been its own subfield in computer vision with its own specialized tasks, its own specialized models, and generation is what
all the text-to-video models are really good at, like all the big diffusion models we've seen the last couple of years. And those are great for creative applications. I want to imagine something that's never been there before. But now with Atlas for the first time, we're putting these two different parts of visual intelligence together in one model. So it can do both 3D reconstruction and generation together in one architecture. So to do that, we had to make a couple changes. One is we had to make it multimodal from the start. So this thing natively works on text, it works on images, it works on videos.
It also works on camera poses as a native input to the model, which I don't think anyone's ever done it to pre-training phase before. And it uses 3D as a native modality that it works on. So this thing from the beginning was designed to be natively multimodal in a way that no one else I think. Sorry, I don't know the space super well. By 3D is this like depth?
or models are like, what does that mean? Yeah, so the formulation we used so far is depth maps. Right? So right now when you have a frame that has a virtual camera telling its position in 3D space, that camera position and camera parameters are a native input to the model. And then what attach to that camera position, you can have both like RGB telling you what does that position in space look like? And you can have a depth map that tells you what is the spatial structure of that position in 3D space. So then text, image, video, 3D cameras.
are these modalities that this thing all does jointly in a multimodal way? I want to add something because I think what Justin just said is actually so important and also what Ben said that it's underappreciated. It's the first time we have a unification of pixel generation and pixel reconstruction. In the world of computer vision, this field has been around for more than half a century.
City here having been in this field for decades, I cannot tell you how many PhD thesis have been written on the problem of reconstruction or novel view synthesis and also our field traditionally
have multiple tracks. You go to a computer vision conference, you have the pixel generation track, you have some recognition track, and you have 3D reconstruction track. This is an elegant model that combines or unifies the problem of reconstruction and generation by anchoring on the viewpoint estimation. And that's just incredibly powerful. Can we take a step back and then maybe you just fill something out? So when you start with the company, I remember you saying,
You want to tackle spatial intelligence, right? And now we have this new model. And so as a lay person, it feels very general to me. You've got next particular prediction, and this is next new view prediction. New view prediction, right? And so like you can get one view instead of views, and you get a new view. Can maybe you pencil out like how this is a significant step to this general problem of spatial intelligence, and maybe by starting to describe what spatial intelligence is? Well, spatial intelligence eventually must enable us to...
both generate what the space is, reason within it, and being able to edit and interact within it. Now we can argue is it 3D or 4D, ultimately it's 4D with the time dimension. But even just 3D, these are the fundamental tasks that one has to do, or spatial intelligence has to enable. And then we talk about with that you can render, you can simulate, and you can plan actions. But
To do that, a fundamental problem to solve is to understand the geometry and structure in the physics of the space. And I do believe Atlas is a significant step forward because now with every single frame, you can generate an estimated important piece of information, which is the viewpoint, the camera pose. And that is the most critical information one needs about the geometry.
of the space, and that can lead to all the emergent behaviors we see in the downstream of the model, which we showed in the blog. So on the path to spatial intelligence, generating pixels is definitely a early step, which we have seen with what you call it, gazillions of models. But generating pixels that are truly spatially contextualized and grounded is absolutely another major step, and that is the very hard step.
that Atlas has taken. We definitely have, you know, we can just keep going here, right? Like there is the fourth dimension of time which will bring in dynamics and there is more higher fidelity, assimilation and delineation of the space. So this is part of the roadmap of spatial intelligence. Great, yeah. I mean, I definitely want to like dig into like where this is going. But first maybe let's talk about
Getting here? How long has World Lab's been in existence? Two and a half. Two and a half, yeah. And so you've actually released models before. So why didn't you just jump right to Atlas? It's so magic, right? Yeah. Justin's team needs a lot of chips. Yeah, you need a lot of GPUs to actually scale things up. So last year we released our marble world model. And that was the first kind of big major world model that we put out. That powers our current marble product.
And marble is really cool. Marble can take images, it can take videos, it can take text prompts and use these to generate 3D worlds. But one of the biggest differences between marble and Atlas is exactly what is that output modality. So marble was really focused on Gaussian splats as an output representation. So whatever you're inputting, it's going to output a 3D world represented as a Gaussian splat.
And Gaussian splats are really useful, right? They're really nice, they're easy to render, they can render efficiently on mobile devices, on VR devices, they can interoperate with other, with game engines, with simulation engines. So there's a lot of nice things about Gaussian splats. But, you know, I think that was kind of a bottleneck in the previous marble model. So what we did with Atlas is redesign the thing a little bit, and we realized that we need to bifurcate these modalities earlier, and actually have all these modalities working in a more unified way in the model.
So now with Atlas, the fundamental primitive is not like a ga... could generate a Gaussian splat world. The fundamental primitive is as we said, new view prediction. And that can generate RGB frames, that can generate 3D, and we can use those to generate a beautiful Gaussian splat world when you need them. But we don't need to bottleneck our outputs through the Gaussian splats when we don't need to. And that was a... that actually took a lot of, you know, blood, sweat, and tears to understand, like, what are all the pros and cons of these different representations? That's one part of it.
The other part is you got to climb the scaling ladder. You got to work your way up and do smaller experiments, do smaller models to build your conviction on what's going to work and what's going to scale. If you could instantly know the right thing that's going to scale, you should just do that. But when we started the company left, the world was a very different place. There was no scaling law of spatial intelligence. When we started the company, the world was in a very different place. The tech was in a very different place. We had a lot of ambitions about where we wanted it to go.
But it took a couple iterations for us to hit upon this formulation that we thought is actually like this is the one that can scale up. You know, Ben, you know, being the creator of Nerf and doing a lot of 3D and reconstruction. So it's not so obvious to me that like if you have multiple views that you actually end up with a 3D thing, but like you've kind of like made a career of ending up with a 3D thing. So maybe talk a little bit about like kind of that step. Yeah, yeah. Yeah, I mean as you said, that's done.
many, many years of my career as a vast majority of my career actually working on producing 3D things from images. And this is actually something we talked about a lot early on in the company, even of like, is this going to be the approach that produces 3D, right? Are we going to synthesize multiple views and then build 3D out of that? Or are we going to try to go direct to 3D? Like, there's been a lot of uncertainty in the field around like, which of those approaches kind of will, we now will kind of like reap the best advantages earlier on. But I did have a lot of conviction just from seeing the kind of
power of what I would almost call the brute force scaling. Scaling in a very, very, very small baby scale, not like real model scaling, but the scaling of dense reconstruction that we had seen happening over the past three years before. So basically we put a- Why is dense reconstruction dense? Yeah, dense. Because I know we're going to talk about sparse and I want to make sure that people understand what is dense and what is sparse. Yeah, so this is actually, even on the kind of like distance and commercial side, I think been one of the challenges of productizing
3d reconstruction technology like at a fundamental level right people kind of don't In a in a casual sense like you think I took three photos of this object or I took six photos of this room like I look at the photos I can Understand in my mind like how those pieces together I can kind of fill in the gaps and get it but there's just never been really any kind of reconciliation between those like really data-driven priors and then the kind of brute force dense reconstruction which
it actually is much more akin to almost like scientific or medical imaging what we did in dense reconstruction, right? You basically have to say every single thing I want to appear in this reconstruction, I need at least three or four views of it. And if you think about that, like even just in this room, right? There's like under the microphone, under the table between every different crack and crevice and the plant leaves, right? To actually truly get a picture that covers every one of those spots.
it's just like very tedious and exhaustive effort to walk around the room. I think you've all seen me running around various places like capturing them. It takes, you know, for someone who's well trained per se, like it can take minutes, but if you hand a casual consumer or even some like kind of professional trying to do this for the first time, an average like cell phone camera or capture device, like it's going to take them probably an hour. I've seen someone for the first time trying to scan a multi room environment spend like two hours walking through it and get enough coverage. And that's just
this very, very exhaustive and tedious loop. And so, yeah, when we say dense, we really mean dense. It's like this room. I mean, you just do like lots of so many photos, right? I want like 100, 200, 300 photos of this room to capture it. And what we're trying to do is bring that down to like three right? Wow. We're saying like 50, 100x reduction. And then that's at that scale where it just completely like flips that calculus on its head of like
what type of captures you reconstruct. You can go back to existing imagery you have. You can go to stuff you find on the internet and even build scenes out of that. You can go to casual videos and like kind of unearth a lot of footage in the past. We would never have treated as reconstructable and go back and like bring it to life as 3D potentially. This is something we've been playing around with a lot with Atlas, right?
taking old clips like I've taken a bunch of my own old captures that never worked before and then put them through the system and then kind of seen a reconstruction of the first time or taking my old captures and thrown away 95% of the photos I took and you know imagine angles that I never would have gotten from a traditional kind of like nerf or splat type reconstruction. One thing that's underappreciated on the website of the demos is the Stanford demo where Ben showed
anywhere between 3 to 25 images you can reconstruct that entire Stanford quad. But the thing is we had to show it from an aerial view. But every single input image is been standing on the ground, taking a picture from the ground. So everything you see are generated but according to the laws of reconstruction. And this is really magical.
And this is where like generation and reconstruction need to interplay in a really fundamental way to solve this problem. Because under the classic kind of reconstruction stuff that Ben was talking about, like the reason you need so many views is because I need like multiple images and I need to triangulate this point in 3D space and see it from multiple viewpoints. So that means like that's required in the traditional version. And on the flip side, anything that wasn't captured in these views, like any pixel that was not visible in one of the input views will be a hole in the 3D reconstruction.
Because fundamentally, like if a thing wasn't visible in the input views, you know, you need to imagine it to fill in the gaps. And that's fundamentally a generative process. So even in this room, even if we set Ben loose with a DSLR and like let him like capture like hundreds of views of this room, even the world expert on doing these dense captures is still going to miss some spots. Like he's not going to get like underneath all of the microphones or underneath all the tables or like in between all the chair legs, you're always going to miss something no matter how many views you get.
So that's where you need generation as another mechanism in the model. Because you're never going to get everything, so you need to have some generative capacity for the model to imagine, oh, based on what I'm seeing, then like first triangulate what I can see, but then fill in the gaps of the stuff that inevitably was not captured.
Yeah, and there's something like super cool about this that LLM have really understood this for a long time right there was kind of almost these like context wars like the first couple years I was like oh we got to 128 to 256 to like 512 we got a million right and everyone kind of understands now at a pretty tangible level to value if you know you crank your context length to high when you're using your coding model it's a hard problem like everyone has a feel for that but like no one has pushed that at all on the image and video model side in the same kind of like principled way like no one's out there trying to like put of
like an hour long video through and do a needle and a haystack retrieval of like a frame at that 37 minute mark. Whereas with reconstruction and generation, you actually have the same exact thing of like reconstruction is just like generation with a really long context and you put a lot of stuff in it. Right? Like that's the way to actually build this continuum where you kind of bridge between those two things. And like Atlas, like being able to like this is something we can never do with marble. Marble had this kind of fundamental blocker of like you couldn't really jam more than honestly like a couple images in.
But at least I can go and I can actually take like a 64 image capture and do like a fly through an entire house and everything is grounded by being, you know, seen or like almost seen or like slightly extrapolated from what's not there.
But you're just getting these, you know, I'm taking captures I did with 2000 images of a multi-room house and taking it down to like 30, 40 inputs and the fly through looks like basically the same. And this is just like totally inconceivable before. And it's all enabled by building this gracefully scaling kind of context window that you can dump stuff into. And so the way to think about it is like the sparseness or the pictures that you physically took.
And then Atlas as a model creates the rest of the views and then we use classic reconstruction techniques. Is that roughly the way to think about it or in some sense? Yeah. Yeah. I mean, that's the beauty of Atlas is like you can take however many inputs you have down to like a single view.
And then you can always use Atlas as this rendering engine to produce anything else you want. You can navigate it. Like the virtual camera. Yeah, exactly. You can say, OK, I have a picture here. I want the picture there, there, there. You can make a couple of those. Then you can stage a dense fly-through. You can do this in sequence because it's an autoregressive model. It's up to you to pick and choose what you add interactively into the context as you generate. The thing that I just
blows my mind is I just have a very simple mental model I I four pictures and then I've got to like have the model extrapolate between them and then it has to fit when you're like it's got me 3d because yeah, yeah like and I always think of these diffusion models as like being visually great but not accurate and so like And I don't even know if there's a question here, but like how is like the room fits like how is it that it's three?
3D consistent? Is it just lots of data or? Yeah, I mean, partially it's a belief in the scaling hypothesis, right? Like, you know, did you, by the way, I have to ask, when you set out to do this, did you know it was going to work? I was pretty sure. That's so, so, so strange. Were you sure? I think three of us have total conviction about the scanning law.
That I think we do. I do think the exact architecture choices and data mixtures is where the devils are in the details. I have watched Justin and his team going from, we really don't know how long this is going to take to, oh maybe, sign of life.
two, wow, this is gonna work. So no one has done it. But I think the hypothesis, two hypotheses, one is skating law hypothesis, another one is next viewpoint prediction. We had a conviction of these two things. So I think I was very convicted that it was going to work. I was not sure it was gonna work this well at this fast.
Right? Like I thought there's a chance that we do this. Maybe it's not clear that like the first cycle of pre-training a new model with a new architecture and a new paradigm, like the first cycle of that working is insane. So I thought there was a chance in which we might have had to do a couple more turns of that pre-training cycle before we got to the level of quality we wanted.
Are we at the end of the scaling for this architecture approach when you need another breakthrough? No, no, we're at the beginning. Really? Without changing the architecture. Yeah, we're basically at the beginning and we're basically limited by compute at this point. Data is very important, as Faithe likes to point out, but everything has a bottleneck and I think the main bottleneck on continuing to scale this thing is actually training compute. During development, we trained a sequence of models. We read about this in the blog post a little bit, but...
We trained a couple models, the first couple rungs of the scaling ladder. And each time we made the model bigger, and each time we trained it for longer, each time we put it on more chips, it got significantly better. And the model size that we showed in the blog post is obviously the biggest and best one that we trained, but the thing that was limiting it was not the scale or the data or anything like that. It was literally like...
We had a deadline of when we wanted to release this thing and therefore we backed up what we could afford to train in a deadline. But here's a little bit of an insider story, right? Like Justin and team are training from the smaller, slightly bigger, you know, having these roadmaps. And then there was one day in summer, early summer, that it's not even the current Atlas model size, it's a smaller model.
and then Ben just then been feed it into, you know, the viewpoint generation. And remember that famous table, the garden table for nerve paper and many papers that overnight I got a slack. I mean, we also the slack from Ben that the camera flew through under the table. With the soccer ball. Yes, with the soccer ball. Is the soccer ball emergent or is that in the original picture? It was real, right? Okay.
That morning, the three of us looked at each other in the eyes and said, that's it, this is, we're gonna build this. Like we made a decision within five seconds how this is just a no one has ever seen this result. Ben, can you talk through maybe more specifically the use cases? So, World Labs has historically had a lot of users that were creatives and they use it for consistency and
you know, like, whatever, 2D images and for movies and for 3D and for games, etc. And so maybe can you talk about how this extends use cases located to the existing ones and then we'll, like, talk about robotics actually. Yeah, sure. Yeah, I mean, it's kind of funny actually, one of the kind of main ways we even saw people using Marvel plays exactly into this new view prediction case. Like a lot of our... Marvel being the previous, sorry, a Marvel our previous product. Like people would take that product, put an image in, get a full 3D scene as the Gaussian splat.
take a couple screenshots of it from different points of view of Leap, right? And we're like, we can just make this image so that's data pro, right? So I think like, and you know, there's a lot of degradation there. They're like, oh, this flag could look better. And it's like, okay, what if we just generatively model those viewpoints without exact modality of control? So I think like, even that core capability of just like view synthesis.
It's sort of been this academic problem for a long time, but in the sense of, oh, you're going to do this really dense capture, like like generative use, and this is a relatively quite a new problem. And we just see so many people who in this creative pipeline, right, people have a multi-stage workflow, right? I don't think there's a single person out there using one monolithic model, not even seedance or whatever for their entire task. People will have this like, you know,
kind of bunch of storyboards and mood boards of images they pull out from like their favorite collection of image models and then they'll go to different video tools and like build those together as keyframes and then they'll go and like clip and edit those later right so we were seeing this like sort of you know niche but very specific use case for marble as just providing that like sanity that you can ground your generations in some kind of 3d consistent world right people you know I don't
I thought with various image models to ask them to give me different viewpoints of a room and every time you can just look and see all those things kind of moved around like it's not stable and even that one seat of a use case I think kind of signals that there's this value and there's hiding under the surface there like there's just decades of people being used to
persistent 3d state like virtually modeling what they would be doing in the real world and having you know a stage and props and like elements there whether it is for a movie or a show or marketing show or like building out game environments like this this statefulness and persistence is so key and how people think about spatial reasoning and like developing an environment over time like people don't think in this ephemeral like
generate a thing, generate a thing, just throw it away, keep my text prompt. People want to build this collection of assets and model a world in that way. So we're trying to provide, again, with this facial context mechanism and other things, we're trying to provide that level of control and precision and the ability to adjust different modalities of input starting with the post images. But we want to give people more control over the elements of the things in the scenes they're looking at and editing and interaction and all that as we go forward. And I think that that
It unlocks further use cases in those areas we're already seeing, but also expanding out into any place people want to create a virtual replication or a pre-imagination of a real-world space they need to build for architecture and construction. I talked to a guy at some point building booths for conferences. There's just so many things in the world you don't think about and need to be fabricated. Every single one of those basically goes through this pretty painstaking virtual design phase. Of that process,
the part where you go into 3d software is kind of one of the most like arduous and like labor intensive parts right now like like taking feedback on a 3d design from kind of like verbal commentary or sketches or really really quick stuff you got from like a creative director or like a design director or an architect or whatever like mapping that back into the 3d representation is like 95% of the work right you can have a meeting get feedback and then you go back and do a week of revisions and that's just because like
Our software is kind of decades old at this point and it just never became as intuitive as you know playing with Legos or like pottery or doing this stuff with your hands or sketching with a pencil. And this is the real place where AI can actually unlock a ton of value for people in their process, whether it's a creative application or something more industrial or design or whatever. And that like really motivates me to kind of build different flavors of our model to cater to those kind of people. Yeah, I can understand
How it helps with the creatives because like marble did it know also how that extends to things like design or architecture But they say you acquired a robotics company. It's just We just talked about it too. I know I know but it's less obvious to me especially in the context of Atlas like how that Maps to robotics so if you wouldn't mind just penciling that out. Yeah, actually Atlas is a key part of the puzzle so
We acquire this company that was formerly known as Cinex and what is their key technology? Right now their key technology is a system that goes from real to some and then some to real. What does that mean in robotics situation? You want to train a robotic arm to figure out how to do cabling, let's say, in an industrial setting. Well, you need a whole bunch of data to first
train the robotic policy to do these cables, cabling activity. And then you want to evaluate if the robotic policy is doing a good job. And then you deploy the robot into the cabling environment.
In order to train what this company, Cinex, and now our robotics team used to be doing is doing exactly what Ben was saying, dense reconstruction. You take pictures of a situation, and then try to reconstruct that environment. It's excruciatingly painful.
takes a long time, laborious, and it really blocks the velocity of robotic simulation real to set, right? So Atlas really is the next generation technology for that. And this is not just for robotics, cabling or anything, we should zoom out and recognize the biggest problem right now in robotics is actually data. One day it'll be chips, but for now it's data.
because it's so hard to collect real-world data where robots are operating.
Not only you need to collect the data of, let's say, the cabling situation or dishwashing situation or whatever, there is also a very important step called randomization. You have to take the same environment and then randomize the conditions. So the cable doesn't literally only bend this way, it can bend a different way or the box can have different sizes, colors, different lids and all that, or in different parts of the scene.
You have to go through a real-to-sum situation in order to get enough of that data in addition to other data you can get from internet. So this real-to-sum step will be really helped by Atlas. That's just the first part of this, is meeting the robotics needs in the current technology because we don't yet have a frontier foundation model that's robust enough for robotics.
But Ageless is a multi-modal model. It takes different kinds of input and generates different kind of output. You can totally imagine the next step is Ageless taking in data that's dynamical and that can really start to bridge the gap between action planning.
and robotics and Atlas output. So that's on that roadmap. Were you going to say? Yeah, I was going to say there's something fundamentally different about training a robotics policy compared to really any other application in AI we've seen before. And that's like if you're generating a piece of code, like you're generating an image, you're generating a video, the model is fundamentally creating this artifact. And that artifact, like there's a lot of examples of artifacts that you can go out on the web or somewhere and collect.
You want to generate images, there's a lot of images out there. You want to generate videos, there's a lot of videos out there. You want to generate a code base, there's a lot of code bases out there you could work from. A robotics policy is something fundamentally different. It's not producing a static thing. It's instead a policy that's going to go out into the world, make actions, and try to achieve a goal. And the world's not always going to respond the way you expect. Unexpected stuff is going to happen. So a robotics policy is fundamentally an agent that is out in the real world interacting with the real world. And stuff happens.
So, you need like a critical part of that is those policies during training need to be exposed to every possible thing that could go wrong during their deployment. And that's where simulation is really key for robotics, right? So, there's the, and then there's two angles on that. Like one is the kind of classical simulation. You can go out, you can go and like go to your favorite physics engine and like try to imagine creatively as a human designer, what are all the scenarios that might happen in this, when achieving this task?
and then try to write explicit code that models them all. That's one angle, and that's an interesting angle with coding agents, like that actually gets supercharged too. But there's another angle, which is try to have more data-driven simulation. Like, maybe we can, can we have a learned model that can understand how the environment, how the world is going to respond to actions? And maybe it might respond in unexpected ways sometimes. Then could we build these neural simulators that are trained on as much data as we can, then use these neural simulators, these learned neural simulators,
you know, as a simulation bed to train robotic policies. And that's a really interesting future direction, Valis. But then it doesn't stop there, right? But once you have, you know, this learned simulator, like this learned simulator kind of already has in its like mental brain, like it understands the world, it understands how the world is going to respond to actions and why doesn't the simulator itself become the player?
Right? That's kind of the core thesis that we've had around world models and their generality. That there's some core stuff that a model should understand around generating worlds, simulating them, understanding how they appear in different situations, and understanding how the world's going to respond to an action is highly related to imagining what kind of action I need to take to make the world respond in a particular way. One piece of feedback that I got. By the way,
Congrats on the launch. It was overwhelmingly positive. I think it was probably the most significant model launch this year. And yeah, we said glowing things. One person who's an expert in the space who I texted was like, what'd you think? And it's great person. It's fantastic. It's amazing, but there needs to be more dynamics. And so it would seem to be at least the robotics case, but generally it was kind of ideal to actually have a world that moves. And so maybe talk a little bit about
that and then any other future directions that a you're comfortable sharing but you think we're talking through yeah, I mean like dynamics is clearly gonna happen like actually We have baby dynamics already and this is something I think people didn't quite appreciate it really highlight in the blog post but like the previous marble world model It was like fundamentally static. Yeah, like the model just like could not handle any dynamics at all and that was just like baked into the model architecture baked into the training like the whole thing was fundamentally static We already knew that that was a big problem post marble
And we already fixed it in Atlas, right? Like the Atlas architecture is already fundamentally supports dynamics. The Atlas training data fundamentally has dynamics. And if you look carefully in some of the videos that we even posted, it actually is. The waves. The waves. The water waves. Yeah. So like some of the examples, there's like waves in the water, like in some of the like generated aerial views, there's like little cars moving around. So like.
Dynamics is actually already in this model. But it's it by the way the dynamic seems very problematic to me if you're trying to reconstruct 3d from multiple views, right? So like are these things like at odds or? No, so actually one of our theses here is that like, you know if you're gonna do fundamental 3d reconstruction You actually have one have no dynamics like you want to be able to model like exact views of the scene with exact frozen time But then like this is actually kind of a problem with our previous marble approach, right like they're like
you can try to find data that's fully static, but that's really hard to scale and really hard to get more of. And the thing we realized is that even in the case where I want static output in the end, the best way to get it is actually expose the model to dynamics. Right? Like expose the model to as much dynamic stuff as you got, as much static stuff as you got, and let the model figure out how to factor out the dynamic stuff. So, especially in like the code, this is like, and this is actually, so again, in the Atlas pre-training already, like it saw a ton of dynamics in the pre-training already.
then the post-training that we did specific to this checkpoint in this release was focused a lot more on static stuff, focused a lot more on spatial movement and less on temporal. But like we already have, we already like I'm pretty sure this, the pre-trained checkpoint already has a lot of latent dynamics in it. And this is something we're going to improve quite a lot going forward. So Ben, does that mean we're going to get 4D video?
You can like go walk around. You can see the smile on their face. So I actually can see like you just stopped now and you only did kind of bigger, you know, faster, better. You can build almost an entire industry. It feels like a very horizontal primitive and if you did nothing else. But other things that are not just kind of bigger, faster that you're excited about the applications you're focused on, which tend to be kind of more on the kind of content creator 3D side.
Yeah, I'm really excited about pushing that kind of multimodal aspect. I think different modes of control is so critical here. I think like
It's super underappreciated, especially in the academic community, how critical it is to add control conditioning to these models to kind of get out what's inside. I mean, honestly, this dynamic versus static, it's definitely not. I'm not sure I even understand what those are. The trustling in layman's language is just our editability here. I think editability is the key here. Yeah. So I mean, this is something we've seen in like sort of single image models and starting this year in video models is starting to be unlocked in terms of, oh, like.
getting that flavor of like multi-turn or really like intuitively interpreting like I want like this person and this object and this thing to happen and kind of combining those all together and like one pastiche without having to do a lot of like manual work with the system like it just interprets it like kind of frontier image models are kind of there right for in terms of editing but we haven't seen that propagate out as strongly into video yet and then into world models right we've seen some really kind of toy examples of oh I can like
put in a sentence and like you know a dinosaur appears or something with these like sort of real-time models. But I want to like turn that up to really industrial strength and make that because like the trick here is you've got to add control but not compromise the quality of the model or it just becomes a party trick basically like it's like no one is going to seriously think about swapping their like cutting edge frontier video model usage for your model if you give them extra knobs but the quality degrades.
So I think it's really that game of like, how can we maintain like the high bar we've set was the outputs we're able to get in the current model and then add all kinds of interesting stuff that people will ask us for in terms of like, I want to interact with the scene or control the layout or control like the identity of the objects and the things that we're seeing within there or control time, right? And I think that's like an access where it opens up like a ton of really interesting product and interface work. The more complexity you add there and richness in terms of
kind of like enabling you to really think about like redesigning almost from scratch the way people interact with sort of like stateful, you know, 3D worlds in the computer. Like that's really the end goal here is getting like all the capabilities you need to build that kind of system. Awesome.
Anything you add to that as far as new functionality that you'd be excited about that's not just bigger better? I think for me, let's go back to the first principle of intelligence. Intelligence is not sitting there stuck and just seeing something or interpreting something when it comes to space and physical space, right? It's really this closing the loop between seeing and experiencing an interaction. So just thinking about going up that ladder is exactly what Ben said.
I think one interesting motion there is this notion of AI completeness. You read this report? Yeah, yeah. So like everyone, I hear about AI complete by the way in terms of LLMs, which is like you have to be basically, you know, like the smartest LM to answer the question what the smartest LLM will need to answer or you have to solve general intelligence. No, no. It's basically it's like it's a
connection to Turing completeness, right? Like the idea being that like a task is Turing complete, like in classical complexity theory, if like I can take any class in any problem in this category, reduce to that one problem. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. So you can take any NP-hard problem and reduce it to 3SAT, therefore you can use 3SAT to solve any problem. Yes, it's a, yeah. So then like the kind of like soft definition of AI completeness is like there's this fundamental primitive that's an AI task.
But if I could solve this AI task in its full broadest generality, it would solve any intelligence problem. And like the classic example at LLMs is like, next token prediction is AI complete because I could like, you know, there's the classic example, I think from Ilya where like, there's a mystery novel and like the thing has to read the whole mystery novel and the final sentence of the mystery novel is like, and the killer was predict the next token. So like, you could basically like frame any kind of intelligence task in terms of that. So clearly next token prediction is something that people believe is AI complete. But I think that's something we're kind of realizing and
Ben was talking about this earlier today is like new view prediction. This primitive that we have in Atlas, especially generative new view prediction. This is also AI complete, right? And because I could take something like
You can have the movie and you do all of the frames of the movie and then like the killer walks out and then you predict the shackley who walks out. Exactly. Not just that, you could say like I want to have a world where like martin is like writing a proof of the remodeling hypothesis. I don't know if I'm gonna be able to do it. And then the next wifey. And he solves the... So to take an evolutionary view, right?
that new viewpoint prediction is exactly evolution had to solve by making animals move. Nature give animals eyes, but nature didn't give trees eyes. Why? Because when you move, you see a new viewpoint. And that is the whether you call it AI complete or intelligence complete. So we do believe very strongly that next viewpoint prediction is
is the equivalent of next token prediction. Amazing. Well, with that, congratulations to all of you on a phenomenal model launch. We're very excited for future model launches and thanks for coming. Thank you. Thanks so much. Thanks for listening to this episode of the A16Z Podcast. If you like this episode, be sure to like, comment, subscribe, leave us a rating or review, and share it with your friends and family. For more episodes, go to YouTube, Apple Podcast, and Spotify. Follow us on X at A16Z
and subscribe to our substack at a16z.substack.com. Thanks again for listening, and I'll see you in the next episode. As a reminder, the content here is for informational purposes only. It should not be taken as legal business, tax, or investment advice, or be used to evaluate any investment or security and is not directed at any investors or potential investors in any A16z fund. Please note that A16z and its affiliates may also maintain investments in the companies discussed in this podcast. For more details, including a link to our investments,
please see a16z.com forward slash disclosures.